<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true representation of the rise, progresse, and state of the present divisions of the Church of Scotland</title>
            <author>Sharp, James, 1613-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33874</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13586835</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13586835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59542)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1048:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true representation of the rise, progresse, and state of the present divisions of the Church of Scotland</title>
                  <author>Sharp, James, 1613-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to James Sharp by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100562:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100562:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE REPRESENTATION OF THE <hi>RISE, PROGRESSE, AND STATE</hi> OF THE PRESENT DIVISIONS OF THE CHURCH OF SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the yeere 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100562:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100562:2"/>
            <head>A TRUE REPRESENTATION OF THE <hi>Riſe, Progreſs,</hi> and <hi>State</hi> OF THE PRESENT DIVISION IN THE Church of SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Diviſion and rent that is now in our Church, (once beautifull and ſtrong in its unity and harmony, as a City compact to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) is matter of ſad lamentation to us; ſo it is a ſharp and bitter pain to our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to be making any mention thereof, or laying out the ſame before any, except in mourning and ſupplications before the Lord our God; acknowledging his righteous and holy judgement therein; confeſſing our provoking him to give us up to daſh one againſt another, by not humble prizing of his mercy, but rather carnally glorying and confiding in our former unity, and not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving it as we ought, for his glory, and the promoving of his intereſts, and deprecating his wrath therein, lying ſo heavy upon us. We could heartily wiſh, that our breach, had it been the Lords good pleaſure, being removed ere now, our differences had been buried in ſilence, and perpetual oblivion, rather then that we ſhould be neceſſitated, yet to give an account thereof to the world: and we are ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100562:3"/>much the more averſe from repreſenting theſe our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, diviſions, and the conſequences which have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thereupon, and the effects they have produced; that this cannot be done without ſome, yet too juſt reflection upon brethren, and their practices; with ſome of whom we have walked to the houſe of <hi>God</hi> in company, and whom we do ſtill love and reſpect, ſincerely wiſhing from our hearts, (as the Lord knoweth) that we might with them ſerve the Lord with one conſent. Nevertheleſſe, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much we, and the truth through our ſides have ſuffered, through miſ-repreſentations that are made of the ſtate of our differences, and the foul aſperoſins caſt upon this Church, and the ſervants and Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, who adhere to the publike judicatories thereof; and contend for the preſervation of the government of the Church, in the due authority and ſubordination of judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories, as by the good hand of our <hi>God</hi> in his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they have been ſettled amongſt us, according to the Word of <hi>God:</hi> And perceiving that it is our Brethrens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in all this, either that they may find wayes to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſome extraordinary and irregular courſe for remedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of evils amongſt us; or at leaſt may keep matters in the confuſion and diſorder wherein they are, that men may do as ſeemeth good in their own eyes, in matters Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick, without controulment from the Authority of the Eccleſiaſtick judicatories: We are neceſſitated for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving of theſe who deſire information, and for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneration and freeing of our ſelves of all conſequences that may follow in this Church, upon the continuance of our confuſions through their miſinſformations, to give a true information, and lay open the ſtate of our differences and preſent caſe of our Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>2</label> For this end we ſhall hold forth, 1. The <hi>Riſe</hi> of our Diviſion, and what were the matters of our differences, that ſo the true ſtate of the controverſie betwixt us and our diſſenting brethren, may be known. 2. Some of the irregular courſes they have run into, and do practice, for ſtrengthening of their party and faction. 3. What means
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100562:3"/>we have uſed, and what we have condeſcended unto, to gain them to union and conjunction with us in the judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Church, but without any ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Sect. 3. As for the firſt head, We ſhall not trouble men with ripping up the ſecret actings of that ſpirit of Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which at laſt appeared in its own colours openly amongſt us) in ſome of them, while as we were yet going along together, and there was no breach between our brethren and us. Albeit it is moſt certain, that before, even long before, that godly underſtanding men, who were upon publike judicatures, and had occaſion to obſerve more neerly the wayes of ſome of our brethren; diſcerned therein principles and deſigns tending to that which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward brake forth. But we ſhall not rip up theſe things; The conception of the ſpirit of Diviſion was too long a being looked to, that it might have been cruſhed; it was now come to ſuch maturity, that it wanted but an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to break forth; which, for the puniſhment of the provocations of a ſinful generation, was by the holy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of divine providence, quickly brought to paſs: For ſhortly after the flroak upon this Nation at <hi>Dumbar,</hi> cometh forth that Remonſtrance, entituled, The <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the Gentlemen Officers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters, attending the Weſtern Forces,</hi> containing matters of great importance, and which was the firſt matter of our publike Church-dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and did produce the firſt open rupture and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the judicatures. Concerning which, theſe things would be obſerved and conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>4</label> 1. It is from this evident, to all impartial ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, That the Church judicatories were far from begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Diviſion, by any reſolutions of theirs (which are now charged upon us as a defection, and whereof our Brethren do make ſo much uſe to carry on their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſigns) yea, they were not ſo much as an occaſion of this rupture: But while they are about their duty, and in the ſimplicity of their hearts, wreſtling with the difficulties of the time on all hands; Our Brethren with ſome others, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive and bring to light this Remonſtrance, deſiring the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100562:4"/>concurrence of the Commiſſioners of the Aſſembly in preſenting it to the State: And albeit it did contain ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny points of higheſt concernment, and contrary unto the conſtant reſolutions of both Church and State (as is after to be cleared) yet they would not lay it aſide for any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, and join with their Brethren, and the reſt of the Nation; but did proſecute it with eagerneſſe and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and upon that account did act in a ſeparate way, from the judicatories and Forces of this Nation, till them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were broken, and the Church and State caſt upon all the difficulties which after followed, and particularly upon theſe reſolutions which our Brethren do ſo much condemn.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>9</label> 2. If we conſider the matter of that Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, it will yet further appear, that they began this rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Church, and that not upon the account of the publike reſolutions, which were not then in being: For in that Remonſtrance, they do condemn, and propund that there might be an overturning of all the reſolutions of the Church and State, taken by them for ſecuring of Religion, in reference to the Supreme Magiſtrate, and that not only all along, ſince the beginning of our late Reformation, but more eſpecially in the years 1649. and 1650. after the State had been purged by the ſecluding of the Malignants, and the concluſions agreed upon, were more ſtrict then any formerly; yea, and theſe who had a chief hand in that Remonſtrance, were very active in carrying on theſe publike concluſions and determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. From which it is evident, that they did begin a rent, by departing from the received principles of this Church, yea, and from what themſelves did formerly judge a ſufficient ſecurity to the cauſe of God, and a great mercy to obtain it: and accordingly, ſome of them were but a little before chiefly active in cloſing Treaties and Tranſactions upon theſe principles, who afterward endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to overturn them This may diſcover to the world, what a ſpirit it is which leads our Brethren in their way; ſeeing they can not only not acquieſce in the determin ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100562:4"/>of the Supreme Authority of a Church or State, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of greateſt concernment to both; nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with the exoneration of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, if they be not ſatisfied; but when themſelves have agreed to theſe things, and have been chief contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them, there can be no ſecurity given, but they will retract their judgements, and overturn them again: Which principle and way is inconſiſtent with the ſafety or ſtanding of any humane ſociety whatſoever. It is true, in their Remonſtrance, and ſince, in their emiſſions to the world in print, they would lay the great ſtreſs of this alteration in their judgement and way, upon after diſcoveries of crooked wayes in managing of Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in purſuance of theſe principles, and of ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars in theſe Tranſactions which were kept up from the judicatories; upon the knowledge whereof, they did ſee the evil and ſin of theſe concluſions of Church and State. But if it were to any purpoſe to trouble the world with ſtories of matters of fact, we could eaſily demonſtrate what a gaining trade they have made of miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this kind; and in particular, that it is more then evident to all who are acquainted with theſe affairs, that theſe reſolutions were faithfully managed, and full ſatisfaction obtained in all that was required previous to a concluſion, and that no particular (though in matters only upon the by, and that whereof they make ſo much noiſe, was only a perſon who was bred in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> his taking the Communion once kneeling, after he had entred on a Treaty) was kept up from theſe who now complain of it; nay, or from the Aſſembly it ſelf, as will appear from the report given in to the Aſſembly, and is now in publike record. But waving all theſe, it is clear from their Paper emitted to the world, Entituled, <hi>The Cauſes of the Lords wrath againſt Scotland,</hi> that they do hold out the very reſolutions and determinations of Church and State in theſe matters, previous to any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, as the cauſe of the Lords controverſie againſt the Land. So that, aſſert what they pleaſe to gloſs the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100562:5"/>they have made a defection from the principles of this Church, and proſecuted the ſame with a rupture and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>6</label> 3. What ever may be ſaid of Supreme judicatories, and their power to recognoſce and re-examine their own concluſions; yet it would be conſidered, that the contrivers, preſenters, and proſecuters of that Remonſtrance, were but private men, or did it in a private capacity. They were ſome inferiour Officers, Gentlemen, and Miniſters at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſome Forces, who took upon them to condemn acts and concluſions of Supreme judicatories unanimouſly concluded, many of themſelves (as hath been ſaid) being preſent, and not contradicting, but poſitively conſenting thereunto; and that concerning matters of State, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government, of greateſt importance: Which any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed and ſober ſpirit will perceive to be a matter above their reach and ſtation; eſpecially to have condemned them by way of remonſtrance, publikely emitted to the world, and preſented to the State; without ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had to theſe judicatories, as once to deſire them firſt to re-examine and take into conſideration theſe acts and concluſions; yea, refuſing to apply themſelves to ſuch a way as that, when adviſed and earneſtly preſſed thereunto, as more orderly, by ſome to whom they did communicate their deſign. And albeit, the Commiſsioners of the general Aſſembly were then ſitting (to whom the management of publike affairs of the Church were committed) and who ought to have been conſulted with in all weighty matters, eſpecially when our Brethren did call in queſtion the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of the preceding Aſſembly; yet it pleaſed them not to own them in this matter; but of themſelves, did by poſitive determination, contrary to the acts of the Aſſembly, prevent their advice. It is true indeed, after thy had concluded the matter, they who were entruſted by the reſt, did preſent the Remonſtrance to the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of the general Aſſembly, deſiring their concurrence in preſenting it to the State; but withal, it is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that when it was enquired, if they had any power
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100562:5"/>to change any thing in it: They anſwered, that though ſome expreſſions might be changed, yet they had no power, and were not to alter any thing of the matter of it, which was in effect, to obtrude their determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Church-judicatorie; As theſe things did evidence their ſmall reſpect to the government of this Church, and their ſtretching themſelves beyond their line, by determining in their private capacity, not only antecedently, but contrary to the concluſions of the Supreme judicatories; ſo divers of theſe who went a long with them in it at firſt, perceiving ſhortly after how diviſive and deſtructive to al order that courſe was, did quickly withdraw from them, repenting that ever they had engaged with them.</p>
            <p>Sect. 7.4. What ever charity might have been allowed them, in preſenting their thoughts upon theſe Tranſactions, or of other faults, for a teſtimony and exoneration of their own conſciences, and deſiring to have them redreſſed in an orderly way by the competent judicatories: yet this can no wayes be juſtified, that not only they ſecond their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony with a ſeparation, but in the cloſe of the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, they hold forth a Declaration, and avowing <hi>of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements upon their hearts</hi> (theſe are the very words) <hi>before God, if he ſhall lengthen their dayes, and take pleaſure in them, to make them any way inſtrumental in his work, and for his peoples good and ſafety; That they ſhall, to the utmoſt of their power, endeavour to get theſe things remedied, according to their places and callings:</hi> Which was a real and plain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging, and banding of themſelves together, to proſecute the matter of their Remonſtrance by arms and force, it being certain that the moſt part of the Remonſtrators then were in a military place and calling. And this, ſeveral paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in their carriage, before they were broken, did clearly enough evidence to be their purpoſe and intention. And the judgement of this Church of ſuch diviſive bandings of parties, hath been ſo well known, eſpecially ſince the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly, 1642. That our Brethren cannot free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of walking contrary to the eſtabliſhed order of this Church in that their practic.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>8</label> 5. Albeit our Brethren, by this Remonſtrance and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100562:6"/>the proſecution thereof, had made a broach upon our ſweet harmony and unity, and laid the foundation of all our fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing breaches; yet the Commiſſion of the general Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly was moſt tender and careful to prevent any breach upon it, as may appear by their tender carriage before they proceeded to give any ſenſe upon the Remonſtrance and from the ſenſe it ſelf which they were afterward neceſſitated to give.</p>
            <p>As to their carriage before, This in general may ſpeak their tenderneſſe, that notwithſtanding their juſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction and offence at theſe proceedings; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the preſent hard condition of the times did call for their preſent appearing againſt theſe dividing courſes; yet they ſuſpended from <hi>October</hi> 24. (which day the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance was given in) to declare their ſenſe of it till <hi>Novemb,</hi> 28. More particularly, when they were frequently conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 14. to cognoſce upon it at <hi>Sterlin,</hi> and had ſpent three dayes in conference and debates about it. They offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our Brethren, That provided they would not require nor preſſe an anſwer to the Remonſtrance from the State, but be coutent to leave it with and before them, as a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for themſelves of their mind and judgement of affairs; The Commiſſion would forbear to give any ſenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and ſhould endeavour and interpoſe with the State, that they would uſe the like forbearance; and accordingly one was ſent to acquaint the prime Miniſters of State with this overture, and they did ſo reliſh it, as they laid that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs aſide, till they ſhould meet with the Commiſſion. This overture and cendeſcention agreed unto by our Brethren, as alſo that in the mean time they ſhould forbear meddling with that debate in publike preaching, was groſly violated by our Brethren. For not only did theſe Miniſters for the Remonſtrance, who preached on the next Sabbath, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely fall upon that debate before the people; but before the Commiſſioners could reach <hi>Perth</hi> (to which they had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed their meeting, on the Tueſday the eaſter, that they might interpoſe with the State) they baſted thither, and gave in a ſupplication to the State, (denying any acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, or reſpect to the Supreme Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtrate, though there preſent) profeſſing their adherence to the Remonſtrance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100562:6"/>and preſſing a ſatisfactory anſwer to it. Wherein albeit they did neglect that peaceable overture, and walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their own condeſcentions; yet the State for ſix or ſeven dayes did follow all peaceable wayes of preventing a rupture; offering that the Remonſtrance might lie as a teſtimony for theſe who had preſented it, of their mind and judgement, and that if they would join with the reſt of the Nation, they ſhould declare nothing againſt it; but nothing prevailing with them, the State was neceſſitate to declare againſt it, and yet in ſo fair terms, as it could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been expected a State ſhould anſwer ſuch a Paper in ſuch a way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>10</label> As for the Commiſſions ſenſe upon it, Three dayes after being ſpent in conference with them, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matters otherwiſe irremediable, and being called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by civil Authority, they judged themſelves bound in conſcience to give warning of that ſnare, and to clear themſelves from being acceſſary to ſuch a diviſive courſe. It is true, the Preſenters of the Remonſtrance, did (after the State had paſſed their ſenſe upon it) propound to the Commiſſion, that they would forbear, till they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted theſe that ſent them; but ſuch a deſire was then juſtly thought ſtrange. For, 1. They had even now preſſed the State, contrary to all our deſires for an anſwer, and men could not ſee how that was conſiſtent with their deſiring now of a delay. 2. The matter had been long enough deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and there had none of the prime contrivers thereof been abſent all the while, that they needed to be ſent for. 3. They did not at all deſire a delay, that they might receive ſatisfaction in any of the particulars Remonſtrated; that ſo they might alter it, in whole, or in part, but only that they might have a hearing to juſtifie their reſolutions therein, to be according to the Covenant. 4. The Commiſſion being required by the State to give their judgement in it, after ſo many endeavours for an accommodation which had proven ineffectual, they could not be wanting in their duty in ſuch a caſe; yet the ſenſe which they did give upon it, will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe how tenderly they walked in the buſineſſe; for herein
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100562:7"/>they do acknowledge what truths are held out in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, though they were not clear that they held them out in an orderly way: they do not at all reflect upon perſons nor offer to cenſure them, nor declare them cenſurable; but do only declare their judgement of things contained in the paper; and though they find in it ſome incroachments upon the determinations of the general Aſſembly, as alſo their medling with matters of State and Civil government, and their engaging themſelves to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour remedies in theſe things they remonſtrate againſt; with all which (and becauſe it is apt to breed diviſion) they were diſſatisfied; yet out of their tender reſpects to perſons, they content themſelves with declaring ſo far, &amp; do forbear all further examination of it, expecting ſuch ſatisfaction againſt their next meeting from the Remonſtrators them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as might prevent all further debate.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>11</label> This Declaration, breathing ſo much meekneſs and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, although it had its wiſhed effects in due time, in the moſt part of the Gentlemen engaged in that courſe; yet the Miniſters who were Remonſtrators, and were then preſent, and other Brethren with them were ſo enraged at it, that in a diſorderly way they left the Commiſion (ſome of them not without threatning expreſſions) and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned afterward to any meeting thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>12</label> The next matter of our Church-differences and diviſions, were the ſo much talked of, publique reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the Commiſſioners of the general Aſſembly, returned in anſwer to two quaeries propounded to them by the King and Parliament. The one concerning the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of Perſons to the Forces then a levying, for the defence of the Land, of the date <hi>Decemb.</hi> 14. 1650. Wherein, after a repetition of the quaery propounded to them, and a Narrative of the States obligation to uſe all lawful and neceſſary means for the defence of the Land, of the broken and ſcattered condition of the Forces of the Kingdom, and the ſubduing of a great part thereof, diſabling the reſt from their own defence, unleſſe there be a more general calling forth of the people: The concluſion and reſolution is this,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100562:7"/>
               <hi>In this caſe of ſo great and evident neceſſity, we cannot be againſt the raiſing of all fenſible perſons in the Land, and permitting them to fight againſt this enemy for defence of the Kingdom; excepting ſuch as are excommnicate, forfaulted, notoriouſly prophane or flagitious, and ſuch as have been from the beginning, and continue ſtill, or are at this time, obſtinate and profeſſed enemies, and oppoſers of the Covenant and cauſe of God; and for the capacity of acting that the eſtates of Parliament ought to have, as we hope they will have ſpecial care, that in this ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral concurrence of all the people of the Kingdom, none be put in ſuch truſt or power as may be prejudicial to the cauſe of God; and that ſuch Officers as are of known integrity and affection to the cauſe, and particularly ſuch as have ſuffered in our former Armies, may be taken ſpecial notice of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>13</label> The other reſolution was concerning the admitting of perſons to places of truſt in the State, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinding of the Act of Claſſes, of the date <hi>May</hi> 24. 1651. Wherein after the repetition of ſeveral deſires of the King, Parliament, and Committee of Eſtates, renewed with great earneſtneſſe (for the ſpace of two Months) to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for a clear and poſitive anſwer to the quaery pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded concerning that matter: It is declared as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Leaſt any aſperſion ſhould be caſt upon us of incroaching upon, or intruding our ſelves unto the Office of the civil Power and Authority; we do declare, that we do not aſſume to our ſelves, and that it is not competent to us but only to the King and Parliament, to make or repeal Acts of Parliament; and therefore, that as the Commiſſion of the Kirk had not hand in making of the Act of Claſſes, ſo neither do we take upon us, to derermine the keeping up, or reſcinding, or repealing of the ſame; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing required by his Majeſty, and Eſtates of Parliament, to give our judgement and advice in point of conſcience, whether or not, conſidering the ground contained in the Narrative of the Act of Claſſes,</hi> viz. <hi>The ſolemn league and Covenant, the ſolemn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of ſins and ingagements to duties, Declarations emitted by the Kirk, and the ingagement and pronnſe made by the Committee of Eſtates, to the Kingdom of England; It be ſinfull and unlawfull to admit to be members of the Committee of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100562:8"/>Eſtates, perſons formerly debarred from the publique truſt, or to reſcind and repeal the Acts of Claſſes. We declare, that as for any engagement or promiſe made unto the Kingdome of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>concerning not admitting unto places of power and truſt, perſons acceſſary unto the ſinful engagement, againſt that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, we know nothing of the nature or grounds thereof, and therefore leaves it to the Eſtates of Parliament themſelves, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how it doth oblige or not oblige in the preſent condition of affairs in theſe Kingdomes: But for the ſolemn League and Covenant, the ſolemn acknowledgement and engagement, and former Declarations, we do find that they do not particularly determine any definite meaſure of time, of excluding perſons from publique truſt, for by-paſt offences, but only binds and obliges condignely to puniſh offenders as the degree of the offence ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire or deſerve, or the ſupream judicatory of the Kingdom, or others having power from them for that effect, ſhall judge conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to purge all judicatories and places of power &amp; truſt, and to indeavour that they conſiſt of, and be filled with ſuch men as are of known good affection to the cauſe of God, and of a blameleſs and Chriſtian converſation (which is a morall duty commanded in the Word of God, and of perpetual obligation) ſo that nothing upon the account of theſe grounds, doth hinder, but that perſons formerly debarred from places of power and truſt for their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may be admitted to be members of the Committe of Eſtates, and the cenſure inflicted upon them by the Acts of Claſſes may be taken off, and reſcinded without ſin by the Parliament, whoſe power it is to lengthen or ſhorten the time of ſuch cenſures, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they ſhall find them juſt and neceſſary; provided they be men who have ſatisfied the Kirk for their former offences, have renewed or taken the Covenant, and be qualified for ſuch places, with the qualifications required in the Word of God, and expreſſed in the ſolemn acknowledment and engagement,</hi> viz. <hi>That they be men of known good affection to the cauſe of God, and of a blameleſſe and Chriſtian converſation; which ought always carefully to be obſerved and made conſcience of, though there were no ſuch Act of Claſſes, to the effect that no perſons get ſuch power and truſt into their hands as may be prejudicial to the cauſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100562:8"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>14</label> Theſe are the reſolutions which have been, and are ſo much noiſed abroad in the world, becauſe of which, our diſſenting brethren have made ſuch ſtirs in Preaching, and in writing, and Printed papers, determining them to be a horrid defection to our Covenants, and forſaking of the cauſe of God, and laying the weight of their firſt divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the reſt of the Church and Countrey, upon theſe, (though unjuſtly, as may appear from what hath been cleared in the matter of the Remonſtrance) yea, and branding honeſt men who concurred in them, or conſented to them, with very odious imputations, and determining theſe reſolutions to be the grand cauſes of the Lords wrath againſt the Land. Upon the account whereof they have ſeparated from, and rent the judicatories of the Church, (the condition of the times contributing thereunto) and by their proteſtations, and declinators againſt the general Aſſemblies, the Church is brought into the confuſions and diſtractions under which we do ſo ſadly ſuffer. And albeit ſomewhat hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken, for vindicating us in this particular, in the obſervations upon the differences in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from <hi>page</hi> 10. to 17. And it is not our work in this Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to publiſh a Treatiſe in defence of theſe reſolutions; yet we ſhall add a few things for clearing of the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>15</label> As to the former reſolution of <hi>December</hi> 14. 1650. we need not inſiſt to declare; That this debate is extrinſecal to our Doctrine, Worſhip, and Church-government; and therefore it cannot be juſtified that ſuch a rent ſhould be made becauſe of our differences about it: That there was no queſtion made by our Brethren, of the lawfulneſſe of the ſervice wherein theſe Forces were to be imployed, which might have added weight to the grounds of their diſſent: That the Country was really in that low condition, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the reſolution (occaſioned partly by our Brethrens ſeparation upon the account of the Remonſtrance) which could not but put State and Church into great ſtraits, and warrant them in their ſtations, to improve all ordinary means, not prohibited by the Word of God, and the uſe whereof is not in it ſelf ſinful, for neceſſary ſelf preſervation;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100562:9"/>And that whatever latitude may be taken in ſuch a caſe, yet the commiſſion in their reſolution, did uſe ſuch caution, that if they be judged thereby (as they ought to be) there can be no defection faſtened upon them, even by them who condemn a general concurrence of fellow ſubjects in caſes of extremity; for in effect they approve of none to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but ſuch as are profeſſed friends to the cauſe of God, and who enter in Covenant for that effect. But paſſing all theſe, we deſire it may be remembred, that our Brethren did not content themſelves ſimply to condemn this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or to aſſert that it was unlawful to take in or imploy ſuch as they are qualified in the reſolution; But running to another extremity, did aſſert, that it was ſinful and unlawful for any honeſt and godly Subjects, to go forth and joyn in an Army, conſtitute according to the reſolution, albeit called and required thereunto by the Civil Magiſtrate, in the caſe of necſſary defence of the Nation, and every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſt in it. And in ſeveral papers did poſitively maintain this aſſertion, and by many arguments laboured to bear it in upon people. The groſſe abſurdity of both which aſſertions may be clearly ſeen in theſe few particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>16</label> Firſt, If we look upon all Nations and States through out the world, it may juſtly ſeem a ſtrange Paradox, and of dangerous conſequence, if once admitted amongſt them, That it is not lawful for the Civil Magiſtrate in the caſe of forraign invaſion, to raiſe an Army, as is qualified in the Reſolution, for defence of the Nation; and much more, that it is not lawful for godly ſubjects to joyn with an Army ſo conſtituted. Yea, albeit that reſolution was more limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſtraight, upon grounds and reaſons of expediency; yet we doubt not, but that in the caſe of the invaſion of a Nation, by forraign force, and when the whole Nation is in common hazard, all Subjects and compatriots, as well theſe that are Orthodox Chriſtians as others, though they were Idolaters, Jews, Turks, or Heathens, may be called ſorth; and that a conjunction of them in Armes, for the defence of the Commonwealth, and their own mutual preſervation, is lawful, yea, and a neceſſary duty, to which the Magiſtrate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100562:9"/>ought to call them, and wherein they ought to concur; eſpecially when their conjunction altogether is in rational prudence, a mean neceſſary in ordinary providence, for their preſervation from the violence of the invading powers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label> As this is the univerſal and conſtant principle and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all States and Kingdoms, wherein there are ſuch differences amongſt Subjects (as moſt part of Nations have ſome one or other of theſe mixtures, and where there is moſt unity in Religion, yet moſt of the Subjects are carnal and prophane) and without which it were no great difficulty for an iavader to make a prey of any ſuch Kingdomes; as ſuppoſe the Turk ſhould invade <hi>Germany;</hi> ſo we ſind Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and godly men in all ages and times have never queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the truth of it, but by their practiſe have gone along with it. To paſſe the example of the primitive Church, where, in Chriſtians were ſo far from making queſtion of this, that a great part of the forces of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire conſiſted of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth affirm: As alſo of Orthodox Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in other Nations, who being joyned in civil Society, with others corrupt in Religion, do make no ſcruple of joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Armes with them; and who may juſtly reſent the ſcandal caſt upon Proteſtant Churches, by the ſtarting of ſuch a debate: We ſhall only mention the example of our own worthy Reformers, who in the caſe of forraign invaſion made no ſcruple to joyn in Armes with thoſe who had been in bloody oppoſition to the people of God, ſo ſoon as they were willing to come off from the contrary party, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe repentance for their former courſes. Witneſſe their joyning with the Duke of <hi>Chattellarault</hi> and his followers, who had been in oppoſition to the Congregation as they were then called. Yea, after ſome diſaſter received by the <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Lieth</hi> after that conjunction, they did not look upon the receiving of him, as a cauſe of that ſad ſtroak, as ſome would make the world believe from Mr. <hi>Knoxes</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>Sterlin:</hi> For in the heads of that Sermon, Printed in the Hiſtory of the Church of <hi>Scotland, Page</hi> 217. <hi>Edit. Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> 1644. in 4. there is no mention of any ſuch thing, but only of their carnal conſidence, that poſſibly they had
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100562:10"/>not ſincerely repented their former oppoſition, and that they who were late come in, were made to feel in their own hearts, how bitter a cup they had made others to drink before them: nor doth he (as our Brethrens Tenets now lead them) preſſe them to purge out ſuch as were lately admitted, but doth only preſſe repentance upon all of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label> But we need not inſiſt on this, to inſtruct what was the judgement of our firſt Reformers in this matter, ſeeing before that time they invited even the very Papiſts, remaining yet Papiſts, to conjunction in Armes with them, againſt the Queen Regent, and the <hi>French</hi> party, as will appear from the Declaration recorded in the Hiſtory of the Church of <hi>Scotland, Page</hi> 179. &amp;c. Wherein as there are many things remarkable to our preſent purpoſe, ſo their exhortatory cloſe ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Page</hi> 182, 183. If you tender true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (<hi>i.e.</hi> if ye be Proteſtants) ye know her Majeſty beareth her ſelf plain enemy thereunto. If Religion be not perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive unto you (<hi>i.e.</hi> if ye be Papiſts) yet caſt not away the care ye have over your Commonwealth, which ye ſee manifeſtly and violently ruined before your eyes. If this will not move you, remember your dear Wives, Children and Poſterity, your ancient heritages, &amp;c. Then Brethren let us joyn our Forces, and both with wit and manhood reſiſt their beginnings; let no man withdraw himſelf; and if any will be ſo unhappy and miſchievous (as we ſuppoſe none to be) let us altogether repute, hold, and uſe him (as he is indeed) for an enemy to us and to himſelf, and to his Commonwealth. All which doth make it clear, that they made no ſcruple of joyning with Papiſts, being their Country men and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patriots, and that even when the quarrel with the enemy was complexe, both for the liberty of the Country and the intereſt of true Religion, they were content, and deſirous that their Country men, though diſaffected to Religion, ſhould joyn with them upon the account of their common civil in tereſt, as they alſo afterward expreſſe in another Declaration, recorded in the ſame Hiſtory, <hi>Page</hi> 197. at the beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>18</label> Unto this judgement of our worthy Anceſtors, ſpeaking
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100562:10"/>ſo clearly to the point in controverſie, we ſhall only add the Teſtimony of a late learned Writer, who in his Treatiſe, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Lex, Rex,</hi> Queſt. 37. pag. 379. ſpeaking of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who think, if the King command Papiſts and Prelates to riſe againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> That we are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in conſcience, and by our oath and Covenant, to help our native Prince againſt them: He ſubjoins,
<q>To which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, with hands and feet I ſhould accord, if our Kings cauſe were juſt and lawful. And a little after in the ſame page, he adds, I ſee no reaſon but the civil Law of a Kingdom doth oblige any Citizen to help an innocent man againſt a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Robber, and that he may be judicially accuſed as a murtherer, who faileth in his duty, &amp;c.</q> And afterward, page 382. after this ſuppoſition and aſſertion, If an Army of Turks and Pagans would come upon <hi>Britam,</hi> one part of <hi>Britain</hi> would help another, which includes more then the conjunction of fellow-ſubjects of one Kingdom: He addes, as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> the King of <hi>Judah</hi> did right in helping of <hi>Ahab</hi> and Iſrael, ſo the Lord had approved of the war; which may give a daſh to the many objections muſtered up from the Lords reproof to <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> againſt the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Reſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>20</label> Secondly, As the judgement and practice of Chriſtians and Churches, in former and latter ages, at home and abroad doth juſtifie this reſolution; ſo the Law of nature doth ſtrongly plead for us in this matter: For as in the natural body, nature hath put an inſtinct in all the members to put forth themſelves for the preſervation of the whole, and one of another; So the practical principles of nature, lay a moral obligation upon the members of a Political body, to join mutually together for the defence of the whole, and their own neceſſary ſelf-preſervation, when they are invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a common hazard. So that in ſuch a caſe, if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate do not put them to it, he betrayeth his truſt; and the ſubjects, if they concur not, become guilty of the ruin of the whole; and as the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. makes uſe of this beam of the light of nature, to enforce that there ought to be no ſchiſm in the myſtical body of Chriſt, or his Church, but all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100562:11"/>the members ought have a care of the whole body, and one of another; ſo by parity of reaſon it may be as ſtrongly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Political body and incorporation of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, in things neceſſary for the preſervation of its being and ſafety, and to repell unjuſt violence. Nor will it ſuffice to ſay, that as the Law of nature, when it obligeth us to defend our ſelves for ſelf-preſervation, doth not allow us to make uſe of every mean for that end, but only of lawful means, which cannot be ſaid of conjunction and aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in arms with men corrupt in Religion, or ungodly in their converſation: For we reaſon not from the Law of nature obliging to ſelf-preſervation and defence, <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> but from the Law of nature its obligation lying upon mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one and the ſame body, ſuch as is the incorporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one City, Kingdom or Common-wealth, in relation to the preſervation of the whole, and of one another, when under the hazard of unjuſt violence and invaſion. And ſo the argument ſpeaks not only for the lawfulneſſe of the end, or the defence and preſervation of the Political body, but for the lawfulneſſe alſo of the means, or the concurrence of all the members for that effect, which doth ſtrongly infer our concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>21</label> Thirdly, As this is the verdict of the Law of nature, ſo we cannot ſee any thing in the Scriptures contrary to this; And no wonder, ſeeing Gods Laws (ſuch as the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo is) cannot be contradictory one to another. Yea, we will find in the word, clear warrant for this aſſertion. But not intending a Treatiſe, we ſhall only touch a few ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals which may clear it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>22</label> And to begin with the old Teſtament, albeit, it need not be thought ſtrange that we bring no Teſtimonies ſo directly ſpeaking of conjunction and aſſociation in arms, betwixt the Profeſſors of the true Religion and others of a differing Religion, as members of the ſame civil incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, conſidering that the Church of God being reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to that one people of Iſrael, their Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth were materially the ſame by Divine inſtitution; So that none could be members of the Common-wealth,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100562:11"/>but ſuch as were alſo members of the Church, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the true Religion, as now under the Goſpel it may be otherwiſe; Yet even then we will find this truth, That albeit oft-times many of that Church did make defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to wicked and (to ſpeak ſo) malignant courſes, yet were they never refuſed or rejected from Church or camp-fellowſhip, when they profeſſedly returned from their evil courſes, although there was no real evidence of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and godlineſs appearing in them. How often in the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> did they turn aſide? and albeit he knew well the generality of them continued graceleſs, notwithſtanding their profeſſions of returning, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.2, 3, 4. yet were they never excluded from joining with the reſt in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary undertakings. So alſo in the dayes of <hi>David,</hi> when Ten Tribes had for ſeven years ſhed much blood, in cleaving to the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> and oppoſing his Kingdome (which was an oppoſing of the Kingdom of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the Type; and a fighting againſt the cauſe of God) and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when they joined in the unnatural rebellion with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> yet, upon relinquiſhing their former courſe they were re-admitted into fellowſhip of Council and arms, with the reſt, who had adhered to the cauſe of God. Many ſuch inſtances might be produced from the Hiſtory of the Judges, and by ſucceeding Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> which might abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly clear this truth, which we paſs as ſtudying bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>23</label> The New Teſtament doth ſpeak more clearly to this point, but we ſhall content our ſelves to touch a few things only, 1. It is evident theſe Souldiers who came to <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> were profeſſors, either Proſelytes, or (as ſome think) native Jews under the Roman pay; And as Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines do from <hi>Johns</hi> preaching to them, and not enjoyning them to quit their military employment, ſtrongly argue againſt Anabaptiſts for the lawfulneſſe of war to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; So it will as ſtrongly conclude the lawfulneſſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians conjunctions in arms with men of another Religion, yea, even Heathens, ſuch as many of the Romiſh Souldiers were. The like alſo may be concluded from the inſtance of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100562:12"/>
               <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> preaching to him. 2. It is an undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truth, that now under the Goſpel, it is lawfull for godly, ſound and Orthodox Chriſtians to be of, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in one civil incorporation with wicked Idolaters, Heathens and Pagans; We ſay not that it is lawful for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Chriſtians to aſſociate and embody themſelves volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, and of new, with ſuch people, being before free and diſtinct from them; But that it is lawful to abide in ſuch an Incorporation, we believe no Orthodox Chriſtian (though Anabaptiſts and fifth Monarchy men may) will deny: as being agreeable to the tenor of the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles concerning marriage-fellowſhip to be kept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a Chriſtian and an Infidel, if they be not forced from it by violence, though it were not lawful for a Chriſtian being free, to enter into that fellowſhip; and Chriſtians continuance in ſervitude to Heathens, unleſſe they be made free. Now if it be lawfull to abide in one civil Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with ſuch, It is alſo not only lawful for them, but their duty which they may not neglect when need requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, to join and concur with their co-members in ſuch actings as are for their kind lawful, which eſſentially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the relation, and are neceſſary for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Incorporation, and the juſt common intereſts thereof, ſuch as conjunction in arms to repel invaſion is. 3. As Chriſt never came to a people with his Goſpel, to make that unlawful which was lawful before to them by the Law of nature (as this conjunction in arms in the caſe already mentioned muſt be acknowledged to be before a people embrace the Goſpel) So we doubt not but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Chriſtians will find that the Scriptures ſpeaking to Chriſtians living under Heatheniſh powers, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to perform to them all things lawful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent to the relations wherein they ſtood to them, doth poſitively warrant them to join with their fellow-citizens in this caſe. And particularly, that paſſage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5, 6, 7, 8. doth clearly evince this, where the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth Chriſtians to be ſubject to heatheniſh Magiſtrates, not only for wrath, but conſcience ſake, and to pay tribute
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100562:12"/>to them (whereby they maintained their wars) and that is a voluntary and active way, upon the account that they are the Miniſters of God, attending upon that very thing, even to protect Subjects and Common-wealths.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>24</label> Fourthly, The other branch of our Brethrens aſſertion, concerning godly mens not joining with an Army ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, it ſo groſſe, that all who condemn withdrawing from exerciſes of Divine worſhip, agreeable in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Divine inſtitution, as a ſinful ſeparation, will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor it: ſeeing by their denial of the lawfulneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence in a lawful neceſſary duty, becauſe of the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin to fellow-actors in it, they homologate with the tenent and practice of ſeparatiſm; yea, we believe that they who are moſt ſtrict in the matter of Eccleſiaſtick com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, will deny that ſuch ſtrictneſs is requiſite in mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary conjunction; eſpecially in the caſe of invaſion. And we are the more confirmed in this judgement, that ſome of the great ſticklers in our debates have ſeparate from the communion of this Church, and that (as they profeſſed) upon the very principles whereby they were led with the reſt of our diſſenting Brethren. Yea, one of our Brethren, now at his reſt in the Lord, being deſired by them to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the controverſie againſt the Separatiſts, after he had ſtudied it accurately for a time, did profeſſe ingenuouſly before his removal, (as is known to ſome of us, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who were ear-witneſſes) that he found it impoſſible to maintain the truth againſt Separatiſts, retaining their principles upon which they had gone againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>25</label> We are not ignorant, that not only againſt this aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as we have propounded it, but even againſt the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which was more ſtrict, a great noiſe is made of objections, from places of Scripture gathered together in heaps. And as to us, this Reſolution is charged upon us, as a defection from our former principles, and a violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Covenant and engagements. As to this laſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lange, we ſhall adde nothing to what is ſaid in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon our differences, pag. 34, 35, 36. Neither
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100562:13"/>ſhall we enter upon a particular examination of theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Only this in the general, moſt part of them are out of the Old Teſtament ſpoken to the people of the Jews then by divine inſtitution, as in their Religion, ſo in their State, ſeparated from all other people of the World; and relate to entering into voluntary and elective confederacies and aſſociations with other Kingdomes or Nations: Yea, and ſome of them for active aſſiſtance unto the Nations with whom the confederacy was made; and ſo do not at all touch our caſe of joint acting in Armes for juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary defence of Subjects of one Nation, habitually and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently incorporate and now in common hazard. And for theſe alleaged from the New Teſtament, They are ſuch as are alleaged by Separatiſts for ſeparation from Churches for the the ſin of fellow-members, (as that 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15. &amp;c.) which yet we believe judicious Separatiſts themſelves will judge to be impertinently applyed to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration in the caſe now in hand. As for that paſſage, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.9. which was continually in their mouths in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, it would be confidered that it was ſpoken in the firſt inſtance to people ſo ſeparate from all Nations, as hath been ſaid: And in ſo far as it may contain a Moral rule for all ages, it doth not hold out any rule for regulating the conſtitution of an Army, but onely the converſation and carriage of a people in an Army going forth againſt an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that they ſhould then eſpecially keep themſelves from ſin and provoking God when they are carrying their life in their hand, as the Scripture ſpeaketh. This appeareth from <hi>ver.</hi> 10.11. where purity is required not only from groſſe open, and formally voluntary ſin, but alſo from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſins and the involuntary iſſues of natural corruption; which we believe fall not under the tryal of men, nor can be followed or looked unto in conſtituting of Armies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>26</label> We ſhall add no more concerning this Reſolution, but this one word; However our Brethren charge this upon us as a defection from our former Principles; yet we profeſſe, we never knew any ſuch Principle owned in our Church, ſo encroaching upon the power of civil Magiſtrates, and ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100562:13"/>to all Chriſtian Nations; And we do for our ſelves diſown and diſclaim it before the World; humbly obte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting all Civil Powers and Churches abroad, that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain no ſuch thoughts that ever ſuch a Principle or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was or is owned by this Church, what ever hath been the judgement or practice of ſome particular men, as to this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>27</label> As for the other publick reſolution of <hi>May</hi> 24. 1651. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reſcinding of the Act of Claſſes, there is ſo little ſaid againſt the matter of it, that we need not inſiſt on it. It is true, not only thoſe who were againſt the former reſolution, but others alſo in the State who were moſt active in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, did with great eagerneſs impede the asking or giving a reſolution in this caſe. But they have their own hearts to examine, whether it was (not diſſatisfaction as to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the matter, but) ſelf intereſt that drave them ſo to do. It is true alſo much is ſpoken to the complex buſineſs and proſecution of this Reſolution; but the Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not therefore be charged with defection upon the account of the Reſolution it ſelf, which was only their deed; for it contains nothing elſe, but a clearing of the Commiſſion that they claim no right to have hand in, or medling with the making or reſcinding of Acts of Parliament: An acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the power of the civil Magiſtrate to ſhorten or lengthen civil puniſhments, conſtituted and inflicted by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as he finds juſt and neceſſary for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; And a reſoluton in point of conſcience (being thereunto required that the State might without ſin take off the cenſures inflicted by themſelves in the Act of <hi>Claſſes;</hi> with poſitive and expreſſe provilion, that they ſhould obſerve the moſt ſtrict conditions &amp; qualification in the perſons, that had been at any time formerly required, All which are ſo juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that we believe no ingenuous and judicious Chriſtian wil carp at them. And therefore our Brethren do but unjuſtly challenge us on this account. They ſay, a deſign was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on to advance Malignants, and to cruſh theſe who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been oppoſite to them; and yet no ſuch deſign can be faſtened on the Commiſſions reſolution; yea, before this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100562:14"/>reſolution was given, they interpoſed for obtaining ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for all that were to be admitted, in that very particular, and did not fail to bear witneſſe againſt ſome who were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the State, againſt whom there was juſt cauſe of exception. They cry out that many of theſe who were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon this and the former reſolution, were but ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial in profeſſing repentance for their former miſcarriages, and it was ſuddenly taken off their hands. But we need not vindicate how injuſtly this imputation is caſt upon many of them who were moſt oppoſed by them, whoſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage hath proved them more ſtedfaſt in the cauſe of God, and leſſe ſeekers of their own intereſts then thoſe that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them. We do only aſſert, that this cannot be laid to the charge of the Commiſſion, who as they walked juſtifiably in holding out the rule, ſo they did receive very few them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but remitted them to the judicatories, charging them to be accurate in the matter, and to proceed according to the order appointed by the general Aſſemblies. Yea, it was ſome of our Brethren themſelves, who did receive ſome of the moſt eminent of thoſe, upon profeſſion of their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>28</label> We proceed now to ſpeak ſomewhat to the third matter of our publike difference; Which relates to the two laſt Aſſemblies of this Church, the one at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Dundie</hi> in the year 1651. and the other at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the year thereafter. Againſt the firſt of which, our Brethren (ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending that it was likely the Commiſſions reſolutions might be approved there) were pleaſed to proteſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined it as unlawful and evil, as to all authority; as they did alſo againſt that which enſued, and ever ſince will have them to be accounted no general Aſſemblies of this Church. The evil of this courſe being ſo notour, and ſenſible in the ſad conſequences thereof, both at home among our ſelves, and abroad alſo among all who hear of our differences, and do love that truth and peace which once was amongſt us, we ſhall ſay but a few things to it, And</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>29</label> Firſt, It may be evident to all who are unbyaſſed, that our Brethren by proteſting once and again againſt the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100562:14"/>Church-judicatory (and being ready and waiting on to have done it the third time, had the Aſſembly 1653. been permitted to fit and conſtitute themſelves) have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and continued a ſad rent in this Church, deſtructive to the very being thereof, if mercy prevent it not. Albeit before this Rent, one of the leading men of that party had declared in a particular caſe, that proteſting againſt the act of a general Aſſembly, or of any delegates having their power, deſerved ſummary excommunication by the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of this Church; yet they have not ſpared when it was for their intereſts, and the times ſeemed to afford them immunity, to proteſt againſt the very being of two Aſſemblies. Whereas had they contented themſelves to have proteſted againſt the approving of the Reſolutions, or any other acts of theſe Aſſemblies, (which might have been a ſufficient ſalve and exoneration to them) we are confident it had been born with, as many ſuch irregular practices and proteſtations of theirs are laid aſide without cenſure by inferior judicatories. But by their overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very being and authority of theſe Aſſemblies, They have taught ill-affected men too many criticiſms upon all the Aſſemblies which have been in this Church; They have learned others by their example, to contemn the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Church-judicatories, as we find by daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; They have laid down a courſe how themſelves (and others, if they pleaſe to follow their example) may do what they liſt, and then decline the Judge who ſhould cognoſce upon their carriage; They ſlight and oppoſe the reſolutions of inferiour Church-judicatories, proteſting and appealing to a lawful general Aſſembly, and yet by their principles they are ſure the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall have none lawful (had they never ſo many) till they be pleaſed to approve thereof. And, they have caſt themſelves upon a ſnare very ſinful and ſcandalous in a National Church, that by their declinatures, they are engaged not only againſt what they think ſinful in the acts of theſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, but that they cannot join in moſt lawful things (were it humiliations upon incontroverſed cauſes) which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100562:15"/>flow from that authority. Theſe are ſome few of the ſad conſequences neceſſarily attending theſe proteſtations, which may abundantly evidence, the evil and fin of ſuch a courſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The evil of this courſe may appear further, if we compare their fact, with the Reaſons upon which they ground it, no wayes like theſe Reaſons upon which the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly at <hi>Glaſgow</hi> condemned ſome former cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt general Aſſemblies; but for the moſt part ſo falſe and irrelevant, that it is to us ſtrange, they ſhould own them before the world, and publiſh them in print. They give out there was no acceſs to many to come to that firſt Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by reaſon of the motions of Armies at that time, and yet (beſide that this is very extrinſecal to the freedom and lawfulneſſe of the Aſſembly) Commiſſioners came from pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces moſt infeſted. They ſay the Aſſembly was infrequent, and yet the Roles of that Aſſembly will evidence it was as frequent as many of the Aſſemblies which they do not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. They alleage that the Aſſembly was not free, but over-awed, and yet ſome of themſelves (who went along with that Aſſembly till the end thereof, though afterward they joined in the proteſtation) may bear witneſs, if they will ſpeak truth, that never did Aſſembly more freely and fully debate and reaſon upon matters, then this Aſſembly did upon theſe Reſolutions. They urge in their proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the ſecond Aſſembly, that many Presbtyeries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſend Commiſſioners to it, and yet they were but ſome, and that where they had power, for which the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly could not be blamed, and ſome others who thought fit not to ſend Commiſſioners, yet by their Letter to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly did expreſly declare they were not againſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the former Aſſembly, and conſequently not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that. To this may be added that our Brethren them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did really evidence their own ſenſe of the weakneſſe of their grounds, in that, though all their Reaſons were clear before the Aſſembly at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Duadie</hi> was conſtitute, yet they forbare at firſt to give in their decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature, but with ſome <hi>ſalvo's</hi> did ſit and join in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly chuſing a Moderator, and acting both in the Aſſembly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100562:15"/>and Committes, for ſeveral dayes, never appearing with their proteſtation, till the day wherein a conſiderable part of the forces were defeat, &amp; the aſſembly were met late atnight to adjourn to <hi>Dundie,</hi> and then very unſeaſonably they gave in it. Yea, it further appears from this, that the moſt part of theſe who now join in that proteſtation refuſed then to go along in it, nor did they after join with them, till the face of affairs were more fully altered.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>31</label> But that we do them no wrong, and may obviate what may ſeem plauſible in their way, to theſe who are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our affairs, we ſhall ſpeak a little to two particulars, whereof they make eſpecial uſe to juſtifie their proteſtations. The firſt is, that many members were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in theſe Aſſemblies, who were guilty of a courſe of defection, in the matter of the Reſolutions formerly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, who therefore were incapable to be members. This is the ſtrong argument whereby they ſtudy to engage the ſimple and well-affected to their party, and upon which they ſpare not in their emiſſions, to profeſſe the weight of their cauſe lieth, and do condemn thoſe Aſſemblies becauſe they approved of theſe Reſolutions. And therefore we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, 1. Albeit the conſideration of the perſons whom they accuſe as chief leaders in this defection, might make them (were they ingenuous) bluſh to declare them uncapable of ſuch a truſt, who for many years, both under Prelates and ſince, have been eminently honoured of God to be owners of truth and purity, and promoters of piety, when others were not; Yet we truſt, what hath been hinted in defence of theſe Reſolutions, and againſt their Remonſtrance, will break this ſnare, and clear where the defection lyeth. And ſo theſe Reſolutions being found to have been their duty, the whole Superſtructure muſt fall. 2. Theſe Reſolutions (what ever they were) were not as yet, nor could be judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially found to be a defection, till the Aſſembly were conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and cognoſced thereupon, and therefore they could not inflict ſuch a cenſure on ſo many formerly Miniſters and Elders, till their cauſe was tried, and themſelves heard. Only when their proceedings came to be tried, they were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100562:16"/>to be removed (as our Brethren know is the conſtant cuſtom) and judged by the Aſſembly, and if they were found culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Aſſembly was free to inflict what cenſure they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. And our Brethren know that in the Aſſembly, 1648. ſuch an exception was not accounted relevant in this Church, to hinder members of a preceding Commiſſion, from ſitting as members in the ſucceeding Aſſembly, and to voice (except in the matter of their own proceedings to be tried and judged) until an account were taken of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. And if they ſhould have been removed before, we ſee not but our Brethren who continued in oppoſition to them, ſhould alſo have been removed with them, that the Aſſembly might have judged of both, though the Aſſembly did freely allow ſuch as were oppoſite to the Reſolutions, to ſit and reaſon, and voice according to their judgement in theſe matters, when the Commiſſion was removed. 3. What over may be ſaid of theſe Reſolutions, and the Aſſemblies approbation thereof, yet it was but one act; and we believe one act (ſuppoſe ſinful) doth not make void and null, the Authority of a judicatorie to all effects; otherwiſe all judicatories might eaſily be overturned. 4. We deſire it may be conſidered, how deep our Brethrens principle will draw. For if theſe mens being in a courſe of defection (as is ſuppoſed) do render the judicatorie unlawful where they are admitted, and oblige men not to join with them in that judicatorie; Then by parity of reaſon they muſt alſo overturn all inferiour Church-judicatories, whereof they are members; nor muſt they join in theſe with them. Nay we ſee not how their principles will allow them to join with them in any lawful act of Religion and worſhip, more then in an aſſembly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>32</label> The next thing they alleage is, That Presbyteries were prelimited in their due election of Commiſſioners to the Aſſembly 1651. by a Letter of the Commiſſion ſent to them, appointing ſuch Brethren as after conference remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatisfied with, and continue to oppoſe the publike reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to be cited to the general Aſſembly: Anſw. 1. This ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing againſt the Aſſembly 1652. where no ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitations
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100562:16"/>were, &amp; yet they proteſted againſt it. They alleage prelimitations in it alſo by the acts of the former Aſſembly. But their conſciences cannot but tell them, that any ſuch acts (to ſay nothing to the matter of them, relating to the publike reſolutions) were ſo far from being put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they were wholly laid aſide, and the Commiſſion of the Aſſembly at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Dundie,</hi> did at a meeting and conference with them, earneſtly preſſe and intreat they would join with them in the enſuing aſſembly; which they refuſed to do, upon the account of the Reſolutions (even though the ſubject matter thereof, and ſo all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of debate about them, was then extinct) and becauſe that Aſſembly had a dependence upon the former, they had proteſted againſt, and had appointed time and place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, albeit legally they could no other way have acceſſe to keep a new aſſembly, but by vertue of the former indiction and appointment. 2. We think it ſtrange our brethren ſhould be againſt all prelimitations in the matter of conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting aſſemblies, and that taking ſuch courſe as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion then took, about emergent ſcandals, or errors, ſhould render an aſſembly null and unlawful. We may ſay it, in our conſerences with our brethren we have found them averſe from joining in an aſſembly with us, without both prelimitations and pre-ingagements. And it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known in this Church, that ſuch courſes as that of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion have bene followed, without any reflexion upon the freedom of aſſemblies. And to paſſe other inſtances which may be, and are elſewhere produced, we ſhall pitch on that parallel of the Commiſſion 1648. Wherein ſome of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren had the chief hand, <hi>In which by expreſſe acts, The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion earneſtly recommends to Presbyteries, to take ſpecial notice and trial of every Brothers carriage in the publike buſineſs; That if any be found that do not declare themſelves againſt the preſent malignant courſe, nor come with their brethren in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reſolutions againſt it, nor give publike information to the people, that they be referred to the next general aſſembly; And if any of them have already declared for it, that they be preſently cenſured.</hi> Here we will not only find a parallel to that done by the Commiſſion 1651. but ſomewhat that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100562:17"/>them: Here, ſuch as were ſilent or joined not with their brethren, nor informed the people, were referred to the general aſſembly. The commiſſion 51. did not meddle at all with ſuch, nay, nor with their continued diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after conference, if they did not actively oppoſe, and by their preaching and other actings, obſtruct the execution of the Reſolutions for defence of the Nation. Here, ſuch as declared themſelves, were to be preſently cenſured by Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries; but the Commiſſion 51. did only appoint op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers after reference to be cited to the general Aſſembly, that they might be accountable for their carriage, as the Commiſſion was for their proceedings, and that they might proſecute (if they had any thing to ſay) theſe libels they had emitted, againſt the judicatories and their proceedings. From which it is clear, that the Commiſsion uſed more tenderneſſe in that caſe, then was uſual and approven for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in this Church. If our brethren (as they do) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to this, that the proceedings of the Commiſſion 1648. were right upon the matter as theſe in the 51. were not, and ſo the caſes are different: We hope what hath been ſaid of theſe reſolutions, will refute that imputation and clear there is a parity ſtill. And however, we believe that matters of formality in conſtituting judicatories muſt be ſtill the ſame in all matters, and what ever may be concluded from the matter, as to one act of the judicatorie, yet it cannot be ſimply null, if it proceed in form but according to former approven practices. 3. It would be impartially conſidered what effect that Letter had as to prelimit the aſſembly in the election of its members, wherein we hope the nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the allegeance will ſufficiently appear. For 1. It is known that Letter was ſent but to a very few Presbyteries, &amp; theſe (moſt of them) after their elections were paſt. 2. It needed not to be ſent to many for that end they mention (viz. to prelimit them in their elections) for many Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries had none at all of their judgement among them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers very few, and however they have emitted to the world an account of ſome in moſt of Presbyteries of their judgment, yet when they reckon again, they will find they have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100562:17"/>ſome, whom they name as theirs, and yet to this day they continue oppoſite to their courſe, and that they could not make ſuch an account then of many, as they may do now; ſince divers taking advantage of the times, and ſeeking their own intereſts, have fallen to them. 3. Whatever they ſay of the Commiſſions deed, or their active prelimita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereby; yet if they ſhall aſſert there was any paſſive prelimitation, either of Presbyteries in electing, or the Aſſemblies admitting of ſuch to be members (in which caſe only it can plead the nullity of the Aſſembly) we may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare that they ſpeak againſt clear truth; for nowith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that letter, the moſt part of the moſt active oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers were choſen by Presbyteries, and admitted and acted in that aſſembly, till it pleaſed themſelves to proteſt and leave it. Yea, further, to aſſert this paſſive prelimitation of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, will ſtrike not only againſt the Commiſſion, but againſt all the Presbyteries of the Land, as unfaithfull and betrayers of their truſt, which were too heavy a charge againſt a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Church. The truth is, the carriage both of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Presbyteries, and Generall Aſſemblie doth make it clear, there was no prelimitation intended, nor practiſed in electing members to, nor admitting them to ſit in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly; for they not onely might, but were actually choſen and admitted in it. Only (as is ſaid) the Commiſſion thought it fit they ſhould be cited thither, and that however they might act and vote in other things, yet the Commiſſion and they ſhould be tried together in that debate, which we believe any unbyaſſed Chriſtian will judge to have been their duty, and very far from prelimiting of the Aſſembly, and an irrelevant ground, on which they ſhould have made a rent, and ſuch an inlet of confuſion upon this Church, as hath followed thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>33</label> Having ſo briefly as might conſiſt with perſpicuity, laid open the true State of the controverſie betwixt our Brethren and us, and the progreſſe of our publique differences, till it came to a ſtated rupture by their Proteſtations; we ſhall now (in purſuance of the ſecond head propounded) give a brief account of ſome conſequences and practices that have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100562:18"/>followed upon this rupture. It may be, and is the matter of our ſad lamentation before the Lord, and we might pour out abundance of complaints in the boſomes of ſympathyſing Chriſtians, who ever were ſenſible of the mercy of a Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches enjoying the ſweet of harmony, that by theſe diviſions ſad prejudices have redounded to the Kingdom of Chriſt among us, that the work of the Goſpel is exceedingly retar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereby, Atheiſm and irreligion increaſed, true Religion and godlineſs expoſed to hatred and reproach, becauſe of the carriage and way of many who profeſſed it, the authority of Church-judicatories enervate and rendred contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; their meetings, which ſome times were a reviving now turned into occaſions of grief to the lovers and friends of Church-Government and order; yea, and the work of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging (which our Brethren do ſo much call for) exceedingly retarded and obſtructed. But leaving theſe before the Lord, who alone can apply an effectual remedy thereunto; we hold it our duty to give an account of ſome of our Brethrens irregular practices following upon their renting from the Judicatories; whereby (as by the effects) it may appear what their ſpirit and way in theſe differences is, and it may be diſcerned what acceſſion they have to theſe ſad diſtempers formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>34</label> Their firſt courſe taken for carrying on their deſign, and ſtrengthning their faction, and which they ſet on foot ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after their firſt proteſtation, was, the convening of great numbers of Miniſters, Elders, Profeſſours and Expectants from all parts of the Land in extrajudicial meetings Wherein after confeſſion of ſins and prayer, performed indifferently by Miniſters, Elders, or others in theſe great meetings, they did and do proceed to determination of particulars, tending to the ſtrengthening of their cauſe, and engaging of others in it, and do give equall power to all preſent in voicing and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining in theſe matters of moſt publique concernment. The Lord knoweth that we do from our hearts approve of the duties of private mutual edification, as they are enjoined in the word, and are recommended and bounded by the acts of our general Aſſemblies, with the conſeat, and to the good
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100562:18"/>liking then of all our Brethren; and we do account it not ſutable to the nature of theſe duties to make a noiſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing our own practiſe thereof accordingly. But we do not ſee that our Brethrens way in theſe is at all agreeable to the Rule, nor conſiſtent with the peace of any conſtitute Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church. And particularly we cannot but reſent in their way, 1. That they ſhould make uſe of theſe religious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, as a ſubſervient mean for carrying on theſe courſes, which we hope by what is ſaid will appear to be moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in themſelves. 2. That by giving out themſelves in theſe meetings as the generality of the godly throughout the Land, or delegates in a ſort from them; they do caſt an imputation upon the bulk of the National Church beſide, who are againſt their way, and do not joyn with them in theſe courſes, as not only wrong in that matter, but as not god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome very few excepted. Which as we know to be a moſt falſe imputation; (not many of theſe, of any rank, who owned the cauſe from the beginning, going along with them:) So it is an evidence of a ſtrange diviſive and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſpirit in our Brethren. 3. That they ſhould take upon them in theſe meetings to determine upon matters of greateſt importance already determined both in State and Church, (as the firſt time theſe concluſions agreed upon by both, mentioned in the matter of the Remonſtrance, were expreſly condemned, was in their firſt meeting of this ſort) for not only doth it reflect upon the eſtabliſhed judicatories, as not worthy to be truſted in theſe things: but neither have they any power of themſelves to determine in theſe things, nor have the generality of the godly whom they pretend to repreſent, power to authorize them for that effect, unleſſe they will joyn iſſue with fifth Monarchy-men, in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concerning the power of Saints. 4. That by their determinations in thoſe meetings, ſo contrary to truth, and the received principles of this Church, and the reſults and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices that flow from them, and all under the name of the generality of the godly; they expoſe piety to hatred and contempt amongſt us; while as men ſee pretenders thereunto ſo abſurd and irregular in their opinions and practices. By
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100562:19"/>this means (we may ſay it with regrate) impiety and irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion have ſpread more within theſe few years, than of a long time formerly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>35</label> Their next courſe for carrying on their work, was the erecting of the pretended Commiſſion from the generall Aſſembly, 1650. as ſtill in force, becauſe of the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended nullity of the Aſſemblies that have ſucceeded thereunto. The ſetting up of this Commiſſion was one of the reſults of their firſt extrajudicial meeting, in <hi>October,</hi> or <hi>November,</hi> 1651. At which time, what they had agreed upon in their meeting, concerning the cauſes of wrath, and the overtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſetled reſolutions of State and Church, was publiſhed as the deed of that Commiſſion, hereby ſuppoſing to add authority thereunto; but in effect branding this Church as infamous; while as they who pretend to have ſupreme power therein for preſent, and give out themſelves to be the only men who have adhered to the principles of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> do make null and void all the publike Tranſactions concluded in the view of the world, do maintain ſuch inconſiſtent principles, and do retract and condemn theſe things, which were held out as the conſtant tenour of the Churches concluſions and declarations.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>36</label> As this was the firſt Act of that pretended Commiſſion; ſo they have ſince from time to time, adjourned and voted the continuance of that power as ſtill in force to this day. And albeit (for any thing we know) they have no authentick Copie of their Commiſſion, whereby they might know their power, what is intruſted to them, and the number which makes a <hi>Quorum;</hi> yea, albeit not only that Commiſſion was legally expired at the day of the meeting of the next Aſſembly, which convened in the year 1651. But albeit the generality of the Members thereof did give up their Commiſſion and proceedings to be tried in that Aſſembly, and were accordingly approved, and a new Commiſſion given (as was alſo done at the Aſſembly thereafter, 1652.) yet our Brethren being but a ſmall number of the members of that Commiſſion, upon a pretence of the nullity of theſe Aſſemblies, did judge upon the validity of their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100562:19"/>againſt them, and ſet themſelves down as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which (for any thing we know) may be a perpetual court; ſeeing they alledge the continuance of their power till the next free and lawful general Aſſembly, and none ſuch can be had ſo long as they pleaſe to proteſt againſt it, even albeit the Presbyteries and generality of the National Church ſhould own it, as they did at both theſe contraverted Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. We know not what can be, if this be not an uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the liberties of the Church; when ſome of theſe who are intruſted with a deligate power till the next Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, do make themſelves perpetual Prelates, and uſurp a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice over the Presbyteries, and their Commiſſioners met in a general Aſſembly; yea, and over the major part of theſe intruſted with them; and ſo do caſt all who ought to call them to an account, that they may ſtill continue in power.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>37</label> A third courſe taken by our Brethren to make and keep a party and faction, is their way of celebrating Communions, and obſerving of publique Faſts: Albeit the general Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in the year 1645. did eſtabliſh an Order for uniformity and preventing of confuſion in the celebration of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherewith this whole Church then reſted well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; Yet ſince our diviſions, our diſſenting Brethren have taken up a new and irregular way. To omit their way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting perſons who come from other Congregations, they do not now uſually celebrate that Ordinance, but they have a great many (ſix or ſeaven, and ſometime double, or more) of Miniſters gathered to it, whoſe Congregations (moſt part) are left deſtitute of Preaching that day; great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences from all the Country, and many Congregations about are gathered at them, and on every day of their meeting (which are <hi>Saturday,</hi> the Lords day, and <hi>Munday</hi>) many of theſe Miniſters do Preach ſucceſſively one after another, ſo that three or four and ſometime more, do preach at their preparation, and as many on the <hi>Munday</hi> following; and on the Lords day, ſometime three or four do Preach before they go to the action; beſides, theſe who Preach to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of People that cannot be contained in the Church.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100562:20"/>Theſe practices, as they are a clear violation of the Order unanimouſly eſtabliſhed in this Church, and do occaſion great animoſities and alienations in ſimple People, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Miniſters who will not imitate theſe irregular courſes; ſo unintereſſed obſervers, do perceive a clear deſign in all this, to ſet up themſelves, as the only pious and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous people, worthy to be truſted and followed in our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique differences. Which if it be not an injury to that ſacred Ordinance, and an improving thereof (which is a bond of unity and communion) to be a wedge to drive on and fixe a rent, let the judicious and ſober judge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>38</label> The like may be ſaid of their publique Faſts appointed by themſelves, and for cauſes which they emit without the concurrence of the judicatories. We ſhall not inſiſt to clear how untrue many of their cauſes are upon the matter, (as determining in our publique differences contrary to the judgement of this Church) nor to aſſert their want of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to appoint Faſts and determine the cauſes thereof, except upon cauſes proper to the Congregation where the Faſt is obſerved; eſpecially upon ſuch cauſes as are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe determined by the Church judicatories. But two things we cannot paſſe in this matter. 1. That a ſtudied ſchiſme and Rent is carried on by theſe Faſts; as will appear partly, if we conſider the timeing of them ſo, as may make the diviſion betwixt them and their Brethren conſpicuous in theſe things. Since our diviſions, the judicatories of the Church have been tender of a viſible rupture in the matter of publique Faſting; and therefore when our Brethren would not concur with them in that duty, they forbare to obſerve week days for that effect (as was their cuſtome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and they would gladly yet be at it, as they do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it where the diviſion is not) that ſo all the people might be about religious worſhip, on days appointed for Faſting, though our Brethren would not joyn in it; but our Brethren not regarding this, do obſerve them on week days, wherein the ſcandalous rupture appears, in that they are about that exerciſe, while their neighbouring Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, (yea and ſometime many in that ſame Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100562:20"/>diſſatisfied with their way, are at work. And partly if we confider their way in theſe Faſts, even ſuch as they obſerve in their Communions; for they conveen many Miniſters, and multitudes of people from all corners about to that work. 2. We are not a little confirmed in our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of a deſign in this, that our brethren do refuſe to joyn in humiliations and faſts with us, and that upon moſt uncontraverted cauſes, ſuch as our calamities, diviſions, and contempt of the Goſpel, &amp;c. Sometime they refuſed to joyn in them, becauſe they flowed from the authority of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies which they cannot own; which we do look upon as a viſible and woful fruit of the needles Rent they have made, by overturning theſe judicatories, as null in their authority to all effects; and ſometime when the faſt is appointed by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned authority of Synods and Presbyteries, they have refuſed to joyn, becauſe they alleadged the cauſes were defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, that is (according to our brethren) becauſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of the Church, and the owning the authority of theſe Aſſemblies, were not brought in alſo as cauſes of faſting. We hope the judicious and godly will perceive this not only to be unjuſt upon the matter, and an injurious reflecting upon their brethren, who require no ſuch thing of them in reference to their real declinings; but alſo to be a very diviſive principle, that men will not joyn in cauſes of faſting, becauſe that every cauſe (ſuppoſe true) is not held out in them; and that they will not concur in lawful duties, on lawful cauſes, becauſe theſe with whom they joyn will not come up to their judgement in all other things.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>39</label> In the fourth place we ſhall give ſome account of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns other irregular practices in the matter of Church-Government and diſcipline, whereby they haue exceedingly diſturbed the peace of this Church, and promoted their own deſigns. We need not relate what alterations are in meetings of Church-judicatories, occaſioned by their contradicting and oppoſing whatſoever is not ſubſervient to their deſign, or concluded contrary to their minde; and what bitter and unjuſt reflexions and reproaches, the judicatories meet with from them in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in word and writing, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100562:21"/>they pack up. We ſhall only point at ſome particulars of their actings, And</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>40</label> 1. Since this diviſion in our Church, ſome Brethren within the bounds of a Presbyterie have erected themſelves as the only Presbyterie of that bounds, and for no intreaty of the Synod to which that Presbyterie is ſubordinate, will they be perſwaded to unite with the reſt of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren within that bounds, for carrying on the common affairs of the Presbyterie; but go on to this day to plant Congregations as they pleaſe. And by their continual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations againſt the Synod, and counter-actings to their determinations, do fruſtrate all the Synods endeavours for rectifying any abuſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>41</label> 2. It is a thing moſt ordinary with our brethren, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude Miniſters upon congregations, ſometime contrary to the mind of the whole congregation, ſometime of the greater part thereof, upon the call only of ſome very few and inconſiderable part of that congregation, whom they are pleaſed to call the godly in the congregation: yea, ſometime Miniſters of other Presbyteries do uſurp power to put in a Miniſter, not only againſt the hearts of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, but of the whole Presbyterie to which that Congregation is ſubordinate. And they do not only thruſt in Miniſters thus in a forcible and violent way, but they do it where the congregation is already orderly planted with an able and godly intrant.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>42</label> 3. Theſe irregularities not ſufficing to ſtrengthen their faction, ſome of them went a further length, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured an order concerning the maintenance of Intrants to the Miniſtry, to be allowed by Commiſſioners appointed for that effect. Wherein, <hi>Scotland</hi> being divided into five Provinces, no Intrant was to have any ſtipend allowed him, without a Certificate from (at leaſt) four of Miniſters and others named for the reſpective Provinces where the Miniſter was to be planted. And however ſome few were named as Certifiers who differed from them in judgement; yet they conveyed the matter ſo, as in no one Province there were a competent number of them to give Teſtimony
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100562:21"/>to any Intrant, though they had been free to act in a courſe ſo deſtructive to the order and government of this Church; yea, in one of the Provinces (and that the largeſt) there were ſo many named, as were a competent number of theſe who had ſeparate from the communion of this Church; from whom little favour could be expected to men cordial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adhering to the Presbyterial Government, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers of that order teſtified ſmall affection thereunto, by endeavouring to put that truſt in the hands of ſuch.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>43</label> 4. Our brethren do ſtrike at the very being of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial government, and make every perſon or inferior judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorie his or their own Supreme Judge, while as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the ſubjection and ſubordination of perſons to judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and of inferiour judicatories to ſuperiour, in the matters of government and diſcipline. But when a man is queſtioned for an uncontroverted fault, if he pleaſe to appeal to a free general Aſſembly (which we know not if ever we may have in their judgement, had we never ſo many) he looks upon that not only as a legal defence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him liberty to bring his buſineſſe to an hearing again, before the Judge-competent, but as a ſufficient warrant to go on in his courſe. Likewiſe if any concluſion of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour judicatorie, be brought by appeal before a ſuperior Court, and if their proceedings be judged irregular and unjuſt, they do preſently appeal, and upon that, go on to counter-act againſt any ſuch determinations. This practice, in matters of diſcipline and government was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in this Church, nor we believe in any Church where the Officers and conſtitution thereof were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be agreeable to the Word of God. But whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Superior judicatory might do as they would be anſwerable, notwithſtanding an appeale; yet the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealler and inferiour did alwayes ſubmit and ſiſt their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, till their cauſe was heard and tried. Otherwiſe, it were in vain to think of a remedy by a ſuperiour judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, eſpecially, when our Brethren have learned a way to caſt all Supreme Aſſemblies, till they be ſure they be of their mind.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100562:22"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>44</label> 5. What ever our Brethren ſpeak of purging, yet they ſhew themſelves very irregular and partial in that work. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we have been moſt tender of them, and ſince the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Dundie</hi> have never cenſured any upon the account of the publike differences; yet when informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is given in againſt any of them as ſcandalous and inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, they decline all trial of the matter, and ſometime for that end, decline the judicatories as corrupt. But their proceeding againſt any of our judgement, where they have power, is moſt diſorderly: For they caſt out men at their pleaſure (and none but ſuch as otherwiſe differ from them in publike matters) having nothing real or relevant againſt them; ſome of them being men, who when they joined with them for a time, were good enough in their account. And when thoſe who are cenſured have recourſe to ſuperiour judicatories for redreſs; our brethren by their proteſtations &amp; appeals do keep their cauſe from being heard, and by their counter-actings (yea, ſometime by tumultuary wayes of ſome of their followers, abuſing theſe whom they unjuſtly cenſured, and affronting Miniſters who execute the Synods acts in their favours) do leave poor men under oppreſſion, without any poſſibility of a remedy in an orderly way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>45</label> Fifthly, (to add no more) Our Brethren have ſtudied to carry on their deſign by reproaches and calumnies ſpread of thoſe who are oppoſite unto them: They have publiſhed to the world in print, that this National Church is guilty of a defection from the Covenant and cauſe of God, many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt are branded as authors and ring-leaders in that defection; godly men are ſaid to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, deſerted, and back-ſliden; The generality of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry are cried out upon as corrupt; we are traduced as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the purging out of ſcandalous and inſufficient Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, yea, the judicatories are accounted unworthy of that truſt, in that they muſt have extrajudicial Committees appointed for that effect. To all which (omitting what hath been already ſpoken, to the matter of our controverſies, and what may be after hinted at) we only ſay. 1. As ſome of theſe aſperſions are (we hope) wiped off, by our clearing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100562:22"/>of the falſhood of the grounds upon which they are laid to our charge; ſo the reſt of them not being the cauſe of their firſt rent, cannot warrant them to continue in it, And of all of them we may ſay, that we hope no judicious Chriſtian will like their cauſe the better, that they are ſo oft put to make uſe of perſonal reflexions and calumnies to defend it. 2. What ever be the clamours they raiſe of the general corruption of the Miniſtry, yet they have been oft put to it, and ſolemnly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to condeſcend upon particular perſons and their ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, that they might be tried; yet for moſt part they have alwaies declined it, which is a cleer evidence of a deſign in it, to keep themſelves in the general. 3. We have ofttimes told our Brethren, that their continuing in their way, doth obſtruct the work of purging, and rendereth the Authority of Church judicatories contemptible; and we have aſſured them that if they will unite with us, we doubt not (through the bleſſing of God) to purge the Church ſufficiently in as exact a way as can be deſired according to juſtice. 4. Albeit our brethren neither do purge, nor will ſuffer us to try any of their judgement, yet we are not wanting in that work to our power, but have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly tried perſons upon informations given in againſt them by our brethren, though ofttimes the reality or relevancy of their informations are not made to appear when put to trial; others alſo we have in ſeveral places under proceſſe, and divers have been purged out in ſeveral parts of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>46</label> Having laid open ſome of the ſiniſtrous courſes followed by our brethren for carrying on their deſign, and of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of this Rupture, We hold our ſelves obliged (in proſecution of the third head propounded) to give an account what have been our endeavours to prevent or heal this wofull Rupture: We need not here expreſſe what hath been the affliction of our ſpirits before the Lord becauſe of our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and our deſires to him for curing thereof, nor what pains we have taken to lay before our brethren the evil of a ſchiſm, and how irrelevant their grounds were (ſuppoſe true) to bottome ſuch courſes upon. Nor ſhall we arrogate to our ſelves (in oppoſition to our brethren) that we could not, as Chriſtians, look upon the wounds of our Mother, but with bleeding hearts; and would account our ſelves moſt unworthy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100562:23"/>of our truſts, if any private intereſt of our own ſhould hinder an union; or if we ſhould not ſtretch our ſelves to the utmoſt, (keeping truth and a good conſcience) to have our breaches made up. But this we may ſay as rational men, we were the greateſt of fools, if we did not thirſt and long after union upon right terms, conſidering that all we meet within our oppoſition to their courſes, is reproaches, and many ſad diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages our Brethren carrying on moſt of all their deſigns and courſes; and our endeavours to prevent or remedy them, being all ineffectual and to no purpoſe, but the exoneration of our own conſciences.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>47</label> That the ſincerity of our deſires, and our reall endeavours for obtaining union may appear, we ſhall only point at three particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Albeit we continued in our diſſatisfaction with their principles and ways, and wanted not competent Church-power generally throughout the Land, to have reached them with cenſures, and did meet with greateſt provocations from them dayly; yet (as we have ſaid) ſince the Aſſembly 1651. we have never cenſured one to this day upon the account of the publique differences. Nay, we hope it will appear to theſe who have obſerved us and them, that we have forborn to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them evill for evill, or railing for railing.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>48</label> Secondly, As we have forborn to give any irritation which might alienate our Brethren, and make them more averſe from peace; ſo our inclinations to accommodation with them were not at all extorted from us by reaſon of any diſadvantages and prejudices we ſuſtaind through our brethrens irregularities and their ſucceſſe in them. But all along from the beginning, out of our reſpect to the peace of our Mother-Church, and affection to our brethren, we were moſt tender and careful in ſtudying to prevent a rupture, and in ſtudying to bind up our breach when they had needleſly made it. We have already declared what the Commiſſions tenderneſſe was in the matter of the Remonſtrance, the firſt ſubject of our differences. Our brethren know what pains was taken in conferences, before the Aſſembly at <hi>Dundee</hi> to give them ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the matter of the Reſolutions, and how it was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if they could not be ſatisfied, yet they would but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100562:23"/>forbear to oppoſe, and actively to obſtruct the execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but all to no purpoſe: It is alſo known how unſeaſonably and abruptly they gave in their firſt proteſtation and declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour; and thereafter immediately did not only deſert the Aſſembly, but left the place of their meeting, retiring to their own homes: So that the Aſſembly could have no opportunity to confer with them, that they might fall upon amicable ways, to take them off that diviſive courſe. Shortly after that Aſſembly, when the condition of aſſairs was ſo altered, as they needed apprehend no prejudice, had the judicatories been never ſo violent, ſome of us did deal with ſome of them, that they would forbear to proſecute their proteſtations, by counter-act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or following any irregular courſe, but would let the matter lie for a time, if ſo be ſpirits of men might now be calmed, and there might be a healing of that rupture. But inſtead of hearkning thereunto, they proceeded immediately to convene in their extrajudicial meetings, to erect their pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and to publiſh ſuch things to the world, and fall upon ſuch irregular actings as did widen the breach, and afford us too juſt ground of fear, that nothing would ſatisfie them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they had all their will; and were inveſted with chief power to manage all Church matters and govern the whole Church. Thereafter in <hi>May</hi> 1652. at a meeting of correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents from Synods, it was deſired that they would joyn in the Aſſembly ſhortly after enſuing, ſeeing the Aſſembly only could apply a ſit and effectual remedy for curing of that breach. But they did not only refuſe to hearken to this deſire, but ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their papers throughout the Land (ſome whereof are ſince publiſhed in Print) perſwading not only thoſe who had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted againſt the former Aſſembly, but all who were not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the publique Reſolutions, not to joyn in electing or being elected Commiſſioners to this Aſſembly: a deſire (beſide the iniquity thereof upon the matter) moſt diviſive &amp; deſtructive to Church unity, and contrary to the Apoſtles rule, of keeping unity in a bond of peace, where there may be differences in judgement about ſome particulars; as we are perſwaded learned and rational men will perceive and judge: And albeit they did refuſe to joyn with us, yet that Aſſembly being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute (and notwithſtanding they did proteſt againſt the ſame,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100562:24"/>behaving themſelves ſo in that matter, as we have no pleaſure to repeat) did not caſt off thoughts of peace, but made an Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to them for peace, wherein all they required was (not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting of their judgements, nor an acknowledgement of the offence they had given by their practices, which yet had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been required of men who had not done ſo great diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Church, but) only that they would for peace ſake, paſſe from their proteſtations and declinatures which had made ſuch a breach upon Church-Government, and led ſo bad a preparative for any who ſhould pleaſe to trace their ſteps, (as a combined party of ſome Miniſters formerly deſpoſed did in part at that ſame Aſſembly) and that they would forbear to keep up debates upon the matters of our publique differences as thoſe for the Aſſembly were alſo content to do. But our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren did not ſo much as once hearken to this Overture, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly rejected it as hoping toſpeed better another way in their deſigns, as indeed they did, ſome particulars whereof are touched formerly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>49</label> Thirdly, Though our Brethren after that time put us out of all hopes of peace, and by their irregular actings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to ſubvert the Government of this Church for ſome years, and by divers means and ways did give unto us matter of ſad mourning before the Lord, and ſerious apprehenſions of the reſult of their practices and ways: Yet as union was ſtill in our heart and deſires to God both in publique and private, ſo we continued in our moderate way of bearing their injurious reproaches, and forbearing to irritate them by any cenſures; though ſometime the judicatories were neceſſitate for their own exoneration, nakedly to anſwer their reproaches, and declare their diſſatisfaction and <hi>non</hi>-approbation of their irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And when we were hopeleſſe of curing our publique differences, at leaſt till we had a general Aſſembly; yet conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the many diſorders following upon theſe differences, we did at meeting in <hi>June</hi> 1655. propound ſome Overtures to our brethren, for preventing the total ſubverſion of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by theſe diſorders, till an Aſſembly might meet, which were rejected by them. Thereafter when they did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a deſire of union (which how and upon what account it came on foot among them, themſelves beſt know) and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100562:24"/>there was a meeting and conference for that effect, in <hi>November</hi> 1655. We gladly laid hold of the opportunity, and laying aſide all prejudices, did ſtretch our ſelves to the utmoſt (keeping truth and a good conſcience) to gain them if poſſible, to an union in the judicatories of the Church. The Papers which paſſed at that conference are in the hands of divers, and will ſpeak for themſelves, and (we are confident) will plead for us in this matter in the judgement of diſcerning and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed men. The particulars of our condeſcentions are too large to be here related. Only let this ſuffice in brief; In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to peace and union, it was offered, that (whatever was our own judgement of the cenſures inflicted upon any by the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> and <hi>Dundee,</hi> yet) we were content that all theſe cenſures ſhould be taken off, and that in ſuch a way as might neither reflect upon the Aſſembly, nor our Brethren, or us; That any Acts ordaining cenſures becauſe of theſe matters ſhould be ſiſted till an Aſſembly, wherein we ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the abrogation of them; that in our after-joynt-actings, we ſhould abſtract from all reflexion upon by-paſt differences; that as to the matter of the Reſolutions, and the two controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Aſſemblies; however we could not in our conſciences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, nor be conſenting to the annulling thereof, yet we did not urge them to renounce their own judgement in either of theſe; nor that they ſhould paſſe from their Proteſtations as a ſtanding Teſtimony of their judgements (whatever we judged they ought to do) but were content that theſe Reſolutions and Acts and declarations concerning the ſame ſhould never be urged againſt them as the definitive judgement of this Church to any effect; that the authority of theſe Aſſemblies ſhould not be urged againſt them; that (however we doubted not of the lawfull conſtitution thereof, yet) enſuing Aſſemblies ſhould be conſtitute according to the conſtitution of general Aſſemblies preceding our differences; and that we would not bind them up, if they pleaſed, from propounding reaſons to any enſuing Aſſembly againſt the publique reſolutions, though we judge they would never be able to bring any ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon againſt them: Only we deſired they would not urge us to renounce our judgements in condemning theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and declaring null the authority of theſe Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100562:25"/>and that they would declare that they ſhould not at any time hereafter make uſe of theſe proteſtations in any judicatory to call in queſtion and annull the conſtitution and authority of theſe Aſſemblies, ſo long as the authority thereof was not urged againſt them; which if they did not grant, we could not but foreſee the ruine of the Government of the Church; We did alſo (beſide other particulars) offer unto them, that not only ſhould Synods take their determinations into a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond conſideration, concerning the irregular plantations of Churches by our brethren, but ſhould follow amicable ways of arbitration by judicious brethren of both judgements ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently to the Synods recognition. As alſo that we ſhould concur with them in all effectual and orderly ways for purging out any inſuſſicient or ſcandalous Miniſters.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>50</label> We hold it not neceſſary to diſcourſe upon theſe our conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſions, ſeeing we hope it will appear, we did ſtand upon nothing which might conſiſt with the ſafety of Presbyterial Government, and with the ſimple not condemning of our own judgements in the matters of our publique differences, which (with more alſo) we did allow to our brethren. Nor ſhall we dive into the reaſons which moved them to decline union upon ſo reaſonable terms, or whether ſome among them were but too active to keep off others who were moderate: We might alſo clear how little they (or at leaſt ſome of them) minded union all along, in that not only in the very time of the conference, they voiced and agreed upon the continuance of their pretended Commiſſion, 1650. and did reſolve and conclude to Petition the Council here, that power might be granted them to purge the Church; but in that all they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to concede, was qualified with this ambiguous Preface, <hi>Of reſerving the liberty of their judgement and practice in matters controverted as may conſiſt with Truth and Peace;</hi> upon which they would never give a clear Commentary though deſired thereunto. But leaving theſe, we ſhall briefly declare what the particulars were upon which the union chiefly ſtuck.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>51</label> 1. Our Brethren would not condeſcend to any union, unleſs the Acts concerning the publike Reſolutions, were rendered of no effect, ſo far as they do import or may be alleadged as the difinitive judgement of this Church concerning the matters
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100562:25"/>contained therein: Which, however they gloſſe the matter in conference, was in effect, that we ſhould condemn theſe Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions in our judgements, and ſhould annul the authority of the Aſſembly which had determined them as the difinitive judgement of the Church. This is no conjecture of our own, but clearly held out in their laſt Paper at that conference, wherein they complain of our not granting of this, as ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and inferring not onely the conſtitution and authority of theſe Aſſemblies, but alſo (in ſhew and appearance) the juſtice and equity of theſe Reſolutions. Whence any man may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that to grant their deſire was not at all to ſuppoſe any Authority of theſe Aſſemblies, but not to leave the leaſt ſhew of the juſtice and equity of theſe Reſolutions. Which if it was to ſeek peace and union, and not rather that we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray and yield up our judgements and the truth (as we believe) let any judge.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>52</label> 2. They would not unite, unleſſe an extrajudicial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of equal members of both judgements were ſet up to manage the chief matters occuring in our Church; Which unto us was a caſting of the Government in a new Model, wholly overturning it, and enervating the Authority of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries and Synods, and allowing to our Brethren at leaſt a negative voice in all matters. This we could not but look upon as a way of Government not warranted by the Word, and more tyrannical than the yoke of Prelacy. And though the whole number had been offered, to be men of our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet we could never hearken to a Propoſition ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Government of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>53</label> 3. They declined alſo to engage themſelves to that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Government, and to obſerve that ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perſons and judicatories in matters of Diſcipline, which we were willing ſhould be mutual. And albeit we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired nothing but what is eſſential to Presbyterial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that which the Aſſembly, 1647. in the Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the CXI. Propoſitions, in the 7th head of Doctrine therein contained, doth approve; And albeit their former actings had given us juſt cauſe to require the ſame might be ſecured for the future; yet they did wholly decline it; which was in effect to make all union void; for had we agreed in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100562:26"/>all things beſide, yet when they pleaſed, they might have ſtept out again at that door, and made the breach worſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>54</label> We have thus briefly declared our mind in theſe matters of our differences, and given a true account of the conſequences thereof, and of our carriage thereupon; Not (the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) to render the perſons of our Brethren odious, nor to be an impediment to Union; but onely for our own vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to prevent any prejudice to the cauſe of God and Government of this Church, through our ſilence, now when they are ſo active in proſecuting ſome deſignes prejudicial thereunto. As we have no greater ambition in the World, then to have this Church united in the judicatories thereof, in its former harmony and unity; and as we drive no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt, nor deſire any thing but what tends to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of this whole Church, our Brethrens as well as ours; So our hearts and armes are yet open and ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them upon ſafe terms, Providing they will not ſeek any thing irregular, and deſtructive to, or our of the channel of the Government. We are perſwaded in our conſciences that the diſcipline and government of this Church is agreeable to the Word, And we in this Nation are obliged by the Oath of God to the maintenance thereof, and to continue therein all the daies of our life: And therefore we cannot recede from it in the leaſt, but are reſolved in the Lords ſtrength to adhere thereunto. And as our Brethren are engaged with us in this Bond (which makes their courſe the more ſad, and grievous unto us;) So we cannot but expect to be encouraged, and countenanced in this Reſolution by the People of God in the two neighbouring Nations, who are bound by the ſame Oath of God to maintain the Diſcipline and Government, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in this Church. But if our Brethren will ſtill perſiſt in their irregular deſignes, and if it pleaſe the Lord (for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſe of this poor Church) to permit them to proceed in them, and to overturn yet more the Government they are bound to maintain; We muſt leave the matter upon the Lord, and wait on him, contenting our ſelves that we have delivered our ſouls, and are not acceſſary nor conſenting unto any ſuch deſtructive innovations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
